Thomas Chester "Chet" Edwards U.S. House of Representatives papers, Inclusive: 1990-2010, Bulk: 1991-2010
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
Thomas Chester "Chet" Edwards U.S. House of Representatives papers
Inclusive: 1990-2010, Bulk: 1991-2010
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
8A
Edwards, Chet
222 document boxes, 130 record boxes, 67 OVZ boxes
The Thomas Chester "Chet" Edwards U.S. House of Representatives papers consist of personal and political materials from Mr. Edwards' 20-year career in Congress.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Chet Edwards was born in Corpus Christi, Nueces County, Texas, 1951 November 24. In 1974, he graduated Magna Cum Laude with a B.A. in Economics from Texas A&M University. He then worked for three years for Congressman Olin E. "Tiger" Teague, who was the most highly decorated World War II veteran in Congress and was known for 32 years as "Mr. Veteran" in Congress. At the age of 26, Edwards was encouraged by Congressman Teague to become his successor in 1978. Congressman Edwards narrowly lost in the Democratic primary to Phil Gramm, but then went on to earn an MBA from the Harvard Business School. In the 1980's, Congressman Edwards worked at the Trammell Crow Company in commercial real estate. Additionally, he owned and was the president of Edwards Communications, a rural radio station in South Texas.
From 1983 to 1989, Edwards served in the Texas Senate. As a Member of the Senate Education Committee, he played an active role in reducing class sizes in Texas' public schools and was named one of Ten Best Legislators by Texas Monthly magazine. Edwards was first elected to the United States Congress in 1990. He served as a member on the House Budget Committee, the Appropriations Committee, and the Financial Services Appropriations Subcommittee, and as vice chair of the Energy and Water Appropriations Subcommittee. He also co-chaired the House Army Caucus.
Congressman Edwards was known as a national champion for America's veterans, troops, and their families. After becoming Chairman of the Military Construction and Veterans Affairs Appropriations Subcommittee in 2007, Congressman Edwards authored a historic $17.7 billion increase in funding for veterans health care and benefits, the largest increase in veterans funding in the history of the Veterans Administration. Chairman Edwards also played a key role in enacting the 21st Century GI Bill of Rights into law, covering the full cost of a college education for our troops. In 2008, both the American Legion and Veterans of Foreign Wars recognized Congressman Edwards' leadership with their national awards given to only one member of Congress.
When he represented Fort Hood, the world's largest Army base, Congressman Edwards played a major leadership role in support of the U.S. Army, troops, and military families. In 2007, he received the Marix Congressional Achievement Award from the Military Officers Association of America (MOAA) in recognition of his work. In 2006, Congressman Edwards was honored with the Award of Merit, the highest award given by the Military Coalition, which represents 36 military and veteran groups. In 2003, the Association of the U.S. Army gave Congressman Edwards its "Legislator of the Year Award." He was co-chair of the House Army Caucus for over a decade and served on the House Armed Services and Veterans Affairs Committees for six years before joining the Appropriations Committee.
Early in his congressional career, Congressman Edwards became known as a leader in the fight against nuclear terrorism, and in 2001, strongly opposed cuts of $100 million to the nuclear non-proliferation budget proposed by the Bush Administration. Serving as a member on the Energy and Water Appropriations Subcommittee, Edwards helped to oversee key homeland defense and university research programs to protect Americans from the threat of nuclear terrorism. To ensure that more cargo coming into U.S. seaports was properly inspected, Edwards supported the implementation of the recommendations of the 9/11 Commission and, in 2003, helped secure $84 million to install radiological detectors at the busiest foreign ports so nuclear materials could be detected overseas before reaching America.
During his 20-year tenure in Congress, including 12 years of seniority on the powerful Appropriations Committee, Congressman Edwards developed a reputation of working hard and effectively for his Central Texas constituents. This reputation was the result of his commitment to protecting jobs and the local economy by making vital federal investments in key education, health, transportation, and water programs in his District. Securing important federal investments for Fort Hood, the Central Texas Veterans' Health Care System, and university research programs at Baylor and Texas A&M Universities was also a primary focus of Congressman Edwards' work in Washington.
Edwards is known as a fiscal conservative who believes massive federal deficits and the multi-trillion national debt are harmful to our economy and morally wrong to pass on to our children and grandchildren. The non-partisan Concord Coalition gave him its "Deficit Hawk" Award. His pro-economic, pro-agriculture record also earned him endorsements from both the U.S. Chamber of Commerce and the Farm Bureau Friends of Agriculture Fund (AGFUND). The U.S. Chamber of Commerce gave him their "Spirit of Enterprise" Award for several years for his support of business. As a strong supporter of Second Amendment rights, Congressman Edwards voted with the NRA 100% on gun rights issues for many years and received the NRA's endorsement.
As a respected voice on issues facing working families, Edwards pushed for increased access to health care for children of working families under the State Children's Health Insurance Program (S-CHIP), supported middle class tax cuts, and protected Medicare and Social Security benefits for America's seniors. As a lifelong person of faith, Chet was honored by the Baptist Joint Committee, and earned the Walter Cronkite Award from the Interfaith Alliance for his principled stand to keep government regulations out of churches and houses of worship. Congressman Edwards also received the T.B. Maston Christian Ethics Award.
In 2008, Congressman Edwards was vetted and became a finalist to become former Senator Barack Obama's vice presidential running mate. Since leaving Congress in 2011, Edwards was appointed the W. R. Poage Distinguished Chair of Public Service at Baylor University. He established Edwards, Davis Stover & Associates, LLC with his former chief of staff, Lindsey Davis Stover, and continues to be involved with veterans issues in the Washington, D.C. area through his work on the boards of the Military Child Education Coalition and the Arlington National Cemetery Advisory Commission.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of records, primarily covering the years 1990-2010, and chiefly documenting Edwards’ career in the United States Congress. The Administrative files contain invitations and phone logs. The Campaign series consists of material recorded from 1990-2010. While relatively small, the majority of the materials include radio and television spot ads for Edwards related to his various political campaigns. Edwards represented Texas’ 11th congressional district until 2005 and the 17th congressional district from 2005 to 2010. The District files contain information about the various cities and constituencies located in those districts and are arranged alphabetically by geographic location. Topics include town halls, Fort Hood, Baylor University, and Texas A&M University.
Legislative files from the 102nd Congress (1991-1992) through the 111th Congress (2009-2010) reflect legislative priorities such as agriculture, appropriations, armed services, budget, homeland security, and veterans’ affairs. Within each Congress, files are arranged alphabetically by topic. Press files generated by Edwards’ office are organized by type: columns, mailers, news releases, newsletters, and radio calls. Materials are categorized as general for their broad scope and are organized chronologically. Newsletters contain documents addressed to constituents and are organized by topic. Speeches range in date from 1989-2009 and reflect Edwards’ service in the U. S. House of Representatives and part of his tenure in the Texas Senate. Arrangement is topical and chronological. Topics include campaigns, commencements, fundraisers, House floor speeches, and impeachment. Many of the speeches are written in Edwards’ own hand.
Topical series cover the gamut of activities and interests over his twenty years of service in the House. Of particular interest are records relating to the Branch Davidians, the Clinton Impeachment, and Religious Liberty. In 1993 February, the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco & Firearms, and the FBI laid siege to the Branch Davidian compound, located ten miles from Waco. After 51 days the siege ended tragically when a fire killed 76 people inside the compound, including the leader David Koresh. Materials include a copy of a response by Edwards to remarks made by Representative Ron Paul regarding the role of the federal government in the tragedy. The Clinton Impeachment proceedings in the House began during the second session of the 105th Congress and were completed in 1998 December. The Senate proceedings began in 1999 January. Of the impeachment proceedings, Congressman Edwards said, “Bill Clinton’s crime was poor judgment and immoral acts, not bribery, not treason, not high crimes and misdemeanors as the Founding Fathers demanded.” Materials include correspondence, Democratic Party press, proceedings, and research on the topics of impeachment, censure, and the Constitution. Edwards was a strong and effective voice on behalf of religious liberty, largely due to the influence of former Baylor University president Herbert H. Reynolds. Religious liberty documents are arranged alphabetically by topic. Each topic represents a major religious liberty/separation of church-state issue that transpired over his time in office. Included among the topics are: Charitable Choice (1995-2007), Religious Freedom Amendment (1994-2002), Religious Liberty Protection Act (1998-1999), and posting the Ten Commandments on public property (1997-2005). Edwards once stated, “The best way to ruin religion is to politicize it.”
The collection also includes Voting Record files that include scorecards and data regarding Edwards’ votes compiled by various special interest groups (Children’s Defense Fund, NAACP and ACLU), the Democratic Party, and his own office. These materials are organized chronologically by congress. Audiovisual Materials include images, audio, and video recordings from 1990-2010. It contains radio and television campaign ads, recorded speeches, press reports, and other recordings. Data formats include: computer diskettes, videotape reels, audio cassettes, Digital Audio Tape (DAT), VHS tapes, Beta tapes, CDs, and DVDs.
The Correspondence series covers a number of topics and is the heart of Edwards' communication with constituents. The last series contains copies of Edwards' 2008 vice presidential vetting notebooks from when he was a finalist to be former Senator Barack Obama's running mate.
Arrangement
A preliminary inventory arrived with the boxes in 2012. Material was arranged into series by office function or topic. Series include: I. Administrative, II. Branch Davidians, III. Briefing Books, IV. Campaigns, V. Clinton Impeachment, VI. District, VII. Legislative, VIII. Press, IX. Religious Liberty, X. Speeches, XI. Voting Record, XII. Audio-Visual, XIII. Clippings, XIV. Correspondence, XV. Vice Presidential Vetting.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 8A. Acquired 2011-02-24
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Thomas Chester "Chet" Edwards State Legislative papers, Inclusive: 1957-1991, Bulk: 1982-1990.
Related references
Thomas Chester "Chet" Edwards U.S. House of Representatives papers, Accession #8A, Box #, Folder #, Baylor Collections of Political Materials, W. R. Poage Legislative Library, Baylor University.
Edwards, Chet. "Chet Edwards: He's Working for Us." 2016.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Clinton, Bill, 1946- -- Impeachment.; Edwards, Chet, 1951- -- Archives.
Subjects (Organizations)
Branch Davidians.; United States. Congress. House -- Elections.; United States. Congress. House -- Records and correspondence.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Armed Services.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Veterans' Affairs.
Places
Texas -- Politics and government -- 1951-; United States -- Politics and government -- 1989-
Subjects
Agricultural laws and legislation -- United States.; Families of military personnel -- United States.; Freedom of religion -- United States.; Legislators -- United States -- Archives.; National security -- United States.; Newsletters.; Veterans -- United States.; Vice-Presidential candidates -- United States.
Genres
Audiocassettes.; Beta (Betamax).; Business correspondence.; CD-ROMs.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Digital audio tapes.; DVDs.; Film reels.; Floppy disks.; Legislative materials.; Maps.; Speeches.; VHS.
- Administrative, 1990-2006; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Administrative materials capture many of Edwards’ day-to-day activities and interactions with his constituents between 1990 and 2006. This includes flag and tour requests and a wide variety of invitations to events both within and outside of his district. Also of note are phone logs and financial records of franked mail. Schedules meticulously outline Edwards’ daily and weekly meetings, and also detail the schedules of the Committee on Armed Forces (1991-1994) and the Committee of Veteran’s Affairs (1991-1994), of which Edwards was a member.
  - General, 1991-2002; 1
    - Congressional Directory, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Congressional Directory, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Congressional Intern Handbook, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Digital Cameras, 2001 Dec-2002 Jan (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - District PC/Move, 2003 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Facebook Page, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Freshman Briefing Pack II, 1990 Nov 27 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Info for Conference Calls, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - House Checking Account, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - IQ (Intranet Quorum), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letter Folder, 2001 Dec-2002 Jan (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Master Stakeholders Contact List, c. 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - New Member, General, 1990 Nov (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - New Member, Committee on House Admin, 1990 Nov (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - New Member, Democratic Caucus, 1990 Nov (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - New Member, Democratic Steering and Policy Committee, 1990 Nov (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - New Member, Democratic Study Group, 1990 Nov (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - New Member, Office of the Majority Whip, 1990 Nov (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - New Member, Receptions, 1990 Nov-Dec (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Office Equipment & Technology, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - PC Comparison, 2001 Nov-Dec (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Printers, 2002 December (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Program for New Members, Notebook, 1990 Nov (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Server, 2001 Dec-2002 Jan (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Supplies, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Supplies & Miscellaneous, 2001 Nov-2002 Feb (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Teleconferencing, 1994, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Texas Legislature Directories, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Constituent Requests, 1991-1996; 2
    - District Appointments, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Flags, A-B, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Flags, C-D, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Flags, E-G, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Flags, H-J, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Flags, K-L, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Flags, M-N, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Flags, O-R, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Flags, S, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Flags, T-V, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Flags, W-Z, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Tours, General, (1 of 2), 1994 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Tours, General, (2 of 2), 1994 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Tours, General, (1 of 2), 1995 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Tours, General, (2 of 2), 1995 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - White House, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - White House, (1 of 2), 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - White House, (2 of 2), 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - White House, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Invitations, 1990-2010; 3
    - General, 1990 December (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - General, 1991 Jan-Mar (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - General, 1991 April-May (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - General, 1991 June-July (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - General, 1991 Aug-Nov (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - General, 1991 December (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - General, 1992 January (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - General, 1993 January (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - General, 1993 February (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - General, 1993 March (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - General, 1993 April (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - General, 1993 May (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - General, 1993 June (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - General, 1993 July (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - General, 1993 August (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - General, 1993 September (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - General, 1993 Oct-Nov (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - General, 1993 Dec 1-Dec 8 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - General, 1993 Dec 9-Dec 31 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - General, 1994 January (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - General, 1994 December (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - General, 1995 January (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - General, 1996 February (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - General, 1996 March (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - General, 1996 April (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - General, 1996 May (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - General, 1996 June 1-17 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - General, 1996 June 18-30 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - General, 1996 July (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - General, 1996 August 1-18 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - General, 1996 August 19-31 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - General, 1996 Sept 1-20 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - General, 1996 Sept 22-30 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - General, 1996 October (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - General, 1996 November (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - General (1 of 2), 1996 December (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - General (2 of 2), 1996 December (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - General, 1997 January (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - General, 1997 February (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - General, 1997 March (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - General, 1997 April (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - General, 1997 May (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - General, 1997 June (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - General, 1997 July (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - General, 1997 August (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - General, 1997 September (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - General, 1997 September (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - General, 1997 October (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - General, 1997 November (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - General, 1997 December (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - General, 1998 January (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - General, 1998 February (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - General, 1998 March (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - General, 1998 April 1-17 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - General, 1998 April 17-30 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - General, 1998 May 1-17 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - General, 1998 May 17-31 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - General, 1998 June (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - General, 1998 July (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - General, 1998 August (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - General, 1998 September (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - General, 1998 October (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - General, 1998 November (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - General, 1998 December (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - General, 2001 January (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - General, 2004-2010 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Mailings, 1992-2002; 4
    - Calendar, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Franked Mail, 1992 Sept-Nov (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Franked Mail, 1993 Jan-Dec (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Franked Mail, 1994 Jan-Dec (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Franked Mail, 1995 Jan-June (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Franked Mail, 1995 July-Dec (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Franked Mail, 1996 Jan-June (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Franked Mail, 1996 July-Dec (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Franked Mail, 1997 Jan-June (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Franked Mail, 1997 July-Dec (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Franked Mail, 1998 Jan-June (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Franked Mail, 1998 July-Dec (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Statements, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Statements, 1993 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Statements, 1994 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Statements, 1995 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Statements, 1996 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Phone Logs, 1991-1998; 5
    - General, 1991 July-Dec (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - General, 1994 Jan-Feb (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - General, 1994 Mar-Apr (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - General, 1994 May-June (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - General, 1994 July-Aug (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - General, 1994 Sept-Oct (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - General, 1994 Nov-Dec (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - General, 1995 Jan-Feb (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - General, 1995 Mar-Apr (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - General, 1995 May-June (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - General, 1995 July-Aug (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - General, 1995 Sept-Oct (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - General, 1995 Nov-Dec (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - General, 1996 Jan-Feb (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - General, 1996 Mar-Apr (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - General, 1996 May-June (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - General, 1996 July-Aug (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - General, 1996 Sept-Oct (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - General, 1996 Nov-Dec (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - General, 1997 Jan-Feb (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - General, 1997 Mar-Apr (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - General, 1997 May-June (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - General, 1997 July-Aug (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - General, 1997 Sept-Oct (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - General, 1997 Nov-Dec (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - General, 1998 Jan-Feb (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - General, 1998 Mar-Apr (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - General, 1998 May-June (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - General, 1998 July-Aug (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - General, 1998 Sept-Oct (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - General, 1998 Nov-Dec (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Schedules, 1990-2006; 6
    - General, Army Caucus, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - General, Committee on Armed Services, 1991 Jan-Mar (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - General, Committee on Armed Services, 1991 April (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - General, Committee on Armed Services, 1991 May (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - General, Committee on Armed Services, 1991 June-July (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - General, Committee on Armed Services, 1991 Sept-Nov (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - General, Committee on Armed Services, 1993 June (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - General, Committee on Armed Services, 1993 July, 1994 Jan-Mar (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - General, Committee on Armed Services, 1994 Apr-June (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - General, Committee on Armed Services, 1994 July-Oct (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - General, Committee on Veteran’s Affairs, 1991-1994 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - General, Conservative Democratic Forum, 1990 Dec (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - General, Democratic Caucus, 1990, 1991, 1998 (Box 28, Folder 1)